The Earth needs no introduction.
الأرض غينة عن التعريف
It needs no introduction in part because the Apollo 17 astronauts,
جزء من الفضل في ذلك لرواد فضاء أبولو 17
when they were hurtling around the moon in 1972,
عندما كانوا يدورون حول القمر سنة 1972
took this iconic image.
التقطوا هذه الصورة الشهيرة
It galvanized a whole generation of human beings
التي جعلت أجيال بالكامل من البشر
to realize that we're on Spaceship Earth,
تدرك بأننا على متن السفينة الفضائية الأرض
fragile and finite as it is,
بشكلها الهش والمحدود
and that we need to take care of it.
وأنه علينا الاعتناء بها
But while this picture is beautiful, it's static,
لكن رغم جمال هذه الصورة، إلا أنها ثابتة
and the Earth is constantly changing.
والأرض في تغير مستمر
It's changing on days' time scales with human activity.
إن النشاط البشري يغيرها بشكل يومي
And the satellite imagery we have of it today is old.
وصور الأقمار الصناعية التي لدينا قديمة
Typically, years old.
عمرها العديد من السنوات عادة
And that's important because you can't fix what you can't see.
وهذا مهم حيث أنه لا يمكنك إصلاح ما لا تراه
What we'd ideally want is images of the whole planet every day.
ما نحتاجه بالفعل هو صور يومية لكل الأرض
So, what's standing in our way?
فما الذي يمنعنا؟
What's the problem?
ما هي المشكلة؟
This is the problem:
المشكلة هي أن:
Satellites are big, expensive and they're slow.
الأقمار الصناعية كبيرة ومُكَلِّفَة وبطيئة
This one weighs three tons.
يزن هذا القمر 3 أطنان
It's six meters tall, four meters wide.
طوله 6 أمتار وعرضه 4 أمتار
It took up the entire fairing of a rocket just to launch it.
ويحتل كل مساحة التخزين بالصاروخ لإطلاقه
One satellite, one rocket.
قمر صناعي واحد لكل صاروخ
It cost 855 million dollars.
وتبلغ تكلفته 855 مليون دولار
Satellites like these have done an amazing job
وتقوم هذه الأقمار بعمل رائع
at helping us to understand our planet.
في مساعدتنا لفهم كوكبنا
But if we want to understand it much more regularly,
لكن إن أردنا فهمه بانتظام أكبر
we need lots of satellites,
سنحتاج للكثير من الأقمار الصناعية
and this model isn't scalable.
وهذا النموذج غير قابل للتحجيم
So me and my friends, we started Planet Labs
لذا أنشأت و أصدقائي بلانت لابس
to make satellites ultra-compact
لصناعة أقمار فائقة الصغر
and small and highly capable.
صغيرة وبكفاءة عالية
I'm going to show you what our satellite looks like:
وسأريكم شكل قمرنا الصناعي
This is our satellite.
هذا هو قمرنا الصناعي
This is not a scale model,
هذا ليس بنموذج مصغر
this is the real size.
هذا هو حجمه الحقيقي
It's 10 by 10 by 30 centimeters,
10 على 10 على 30 سنتمتر
it weighs four kilograms,
ويزن 4 كيلوغرامات
and we've stuffed the latest and greatest electronics
ولقد حشونا هذه العلبة الصغيرة
and sensor systems into this little package
بآخر وأفضل الإلكترونيات وأنظمة الاستشعار
so that even though this is really small,
بحيث يلتقط رغم حجمه الصغير
even though it weighs one thousandth of the mass.
وذلك رغم أنه يزن واحد في الألف من كتلته
And we call this satellite "Dove" — Thank you.
ونسمي هذا القمر "بالحمامة" — شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
We call this satellite "Dove,"
أسميناه "الحمامة"
and we call it "Dove" because satellites are typically named
لأنه عادة ما يطلق على الأقمار الصناعية
after birds, but normally birds of prey:
أسماء للطيور، طيور جارحة
like Eagle, Hawk, Swoop, Kill, I don't know,
مثل النسر والصقر والمنقض والقاتل وغيرها
Kestrel, these sort of things.
والعوسق وأشياء من هذا القبيل
But ours have a humanitarian mission,
لكن أقمارنا لديها مهمة إنسانية
so we wanted to call them Doves.
لدى أردنا تسميتها بالحَمَامة
And we haven't just built them, though.
لم نكتفي ببنائها وحسب
We've launched them.
بل أطلقناها
And not just one, but many.
ليس قمرا واحدا بل العديد منها
It all started in our garage.
وبدأ الأمر كله بمرآبنا
Yes, we built our first satellite prototype in our garage.
نعم، بنينا أول نموذج لقمرنا بمرآبنا
Now, this is pretty normal for a Silicon Valley company that we are,
لكنه أمر طبيعي لشركة مثلنا بسيليكون فالي
but we believe it's the first time for a space company.
لكن نعتقد أنها سابقة بتاريخ شركات الفضاء
And that's not the only trick we learned from Silicon Valley.
وهي ليست الخدعة الوحيدة التي تعلمناها
We rapidly prototype our satellites.
حيث أننا نبني أقمارنا بسرعة
We use "release early, release often" on our software.
ونطبق سياسة "أطلق مبكرا ودائما" لبرامجنا
And we take a different risk approach.
وننهج مقاربة مجازفة مختلفة
We take them outside and test them.
حيث نختبر أقمارنا خارجا
We even put satellites in space just to test the satellites,
بل أننا نرسلها للفضاء للاختبار فقط
and we've learned to manufacture our satellites at scale.
وتعلمنا كيفية بنائها على نطاق واسع
We've used modern production techniques
وقد استخدمنا تقنيات عصرية
so we can build large numbers of them,
لإنتاج عدد أكبر من الأقمار الصناعية
I think for the first time.
وأظن أنها سابقة أيضا.
We call it agile aerospace,
ونسمي ذلك بالمرونة الفضائية
is the idea of democratizing access to satellite information.
هي فكرة دمقرطة الوصول لمعلومات هذه الأقمار
In fact, the founders of our company, Chris, Robbie and I,
الحقيقة أن مؤسسي الشركة كريس وروبل وأنا
we met over 15 years ago at the United Nations
التقينا منذ 15 سنة بالأمم المتحدة
when they were hosting a conference about exactly that question:
خلال تنظيمها لمؤتمر حول السؤال التالي:
How do you use satellites to help humanity?
كيف يمكن لاستخدام الأقمار مساعدة البشرية؟
or with climate change?
أو في تغير المناخ؟
And this is what has bonded us.
وكان هذا ما جمع بيننا
Our entire team is passionate about using satellites to help humanity.
كل الفريق متحمس لفكرة استخدام الأقمار
You could say we're space geeks,
يمكنكم القول بأننا مهوسون بالفضاء
but not only do we care about what's up there,
لكن لسنا مهتمين بما يجري في الأعلى فقط
we care about what's down here, too.
بل بما يجري هنا أيضا
I'm going to show you a video
سأعرض عليكم فيديو
from just four weeks ago of two of our satellites
التقط منذ 4 أسابيع فقط لقمرين لنا
being launched from the International Space Station.
خلال إطلاقهما من محطة الفضاء الدولية
This is not an animation,
هذه ليست رسوم متحركة
this is a video taken by the astronaut looking out of the window.
هذا فيديو صوره رائد فضاء من نافذة المحطة
It gives you a bit of a sense of scale of our two satellites.
وهذا يعطيكم فكرة عن حجم قمرينا
It's like some of the smallest satellites ever
إنها نوعا ما أصغر الأقمار
are being launched from the biggest satellite ever.
يطلقها أكبر الأقمار على الإطلاق
And right at the end, the solar array glints in the sun.
وستشاهدون الألواح الشمسية تعكس أشعة الشمس
Boom! Yeah. It's the money shot.
بووم! إنه صوت المال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we didn't just launch two of them like this,
الحقيقة، لم نطلق فقط قمرين بهذا الشكل
we launched 28 of them.
بل أطلقنا 28 قمرا
It's the largest constellation of Earth-imaging satellites in human history,
إنها أكبر كوكبة أقمار لتصوير الأرض بالتاريخ
and it's going to provide a completely radical new data set
وستوفر مجموعة بيانات جديدة تماما
about our changing planet.
عن كوكبنا المتغير
But that's just the beginning.
لكنها ليست سوى البداية
You see, we're going to launch more than 100 of these satellites
لأننا سنطلق أكثر من 100 قمر
like these over the course of the next year.
كهذه الأقمار في السنة المقبلة
It's going to be the largest constellation of satellites in human history.
ستكون أكبر كوكبة أقمار صناعية في التاريخ
And this is what it's going to do:
وهذا ما ستفعله:
Acting in a single-orbit plane that stays fixed with respect to the sun,
ستعمل في مدارات خاصة ثابتة حسب الشمس
the Earth rotates underneath.
وستدور الأرض تحتها
They're all cameras pointed down,
ستوجه جميع عدساتها نحو الأرض
and they slowly scan across as the Earth rotates underneath.
وستمسح سطحها ببطء بينما هي تدور تحتها
The Earth rotates every 24 hours,
بما أن الأرض تكمل دورتها كل 24 ساعة
so we scan every point on the planet every 24 hours.
فإننا سنمسح كل نقطة على السطح كل 24 ساعة
It's a line scanner for the planet.
سنمسح كل خط طول على الكوكب
We don't take a picture of anywhere on the planet every day,
نحن لا نلتقط يوميا صور عشوائية للأرض
we take a picture of every single place on the planet every day.
بل نصور يوميا كل مكان على الكوكب
Even though we launched these just a couple of weeks ago,
ورغم أنها أطلقت فقط منذ بضعة أسابيع
we've already got some initial imagery from the satellites
فقد حصلنا بالفعل على بعض الصور الأولية
and I'm going to show it publicly for the first time right now.
وسأعرضها الآن علنيا ولأول مرة
This is the very first picture taken by our satellite.
هذه أول صورة التقطها قمرنا الصناعي
It happened to be over UC-Davis' campus
وكان يمر فوق حرم جامعة كاليفورنيا، دافيس
in California when we turned the camera on.
عندما شغلنا الكاميرا
But what's even cooler is when
لكن الأمر المثير هو أنه عندما
we compare it to the previous latest image of that area,
قارناها بآخر صورة التقطت لهذه المنطقة
which was taken many months ago.
وذلك منذ أشهر عديدة
And the image on the left is from our satellite,
الصورة على اليسار التقطها قمرنا الصناعي
and we see buildings are being built.
ونشاهد أشغال البناء الجارية
The general point is that we will be able to track urban growth as it happens
الشاهد أنه سنتمكن من مراقبة النمو العمراني
around the whole world in all cities, every day.
حول العالم في جميع المدن كل يوم
Water as well.
ونفس الشيء للماء
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We'll be able to see the extent of all water bodies
سنتمكن من مراقبة المسطحات المائية
around the whole world every day and help water security.
حول العالم كل يوم والمساعدة بالأمن المائي
From water security to food security.
من الأمن المائي إلى الأمن الغذائي
We'll see crops as they grow in all the fields
سنراقب المحاصيل وهي تنمو في كل الحقول
in every farmer's field around the planet every day.
في كل مزرعة حول العالم في كل يوم
and help them to improve crop yield.
ومساعدتهم على زيادة محاصيلهم
This is a beautiful image that was taken
هذه صورة جميلة التقطت منذ بضع ساعات فقط
just a few hours ago when the satellite was flying over Argentina.
عندما مر القمر فوق الأرجنتين
The general point is
الشاهد في الأمر هو أنه
I've mentioned a few, but there's others:
أشرت إلى بعضها ولكن هناك طرق أخرى:
deforestation, the ice caps melting.
إزالة الغابات وذوبان القطبين
We can track all of these things, every tree on the planet every day.
يمكننا مراقبة كل ذلك، بل كل شجرة يوميا
If you took the difference between today's image and yesterday's image,
وإذا لاحظتم الفرق بين صورة اليوم والبارحة
And we have decided, therefore, that the best thing that we could do with our data
لذا، قررنا أن أفضل ما سنفعله ببياناتنا
is to ensure universal access to it.
هو ضمان وصول الجميع إليها
We want to ensure everyone can see it.
نود أن نضمن للجميع إمكانية الاطلاع عليها
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)
We want to empower NGOs and companies and scientists and journalists
نود تمكين المنظمات الغير حكومية والشركات
We want to enable the developer community to run their apps on our data.
أن يستعمل المطورين بياناتنا في تطبيقاتهم
In short, we want to democratize access to information about our planet.
باختصار، نود دمقرطة حق الوصول للمعلومات
Which brings me back to this.
مما يعيدني إلى هذه
You see, this will be an entirely new global data set.
ستكون مجموعة بيانات عالمية جديدة بالكامل
And we believe that together,
ونحن نؤمن بأننا جميعا
we can help to take care of our Spaceship Earth.
يمكن أن نساعد بحماية سفينتنا الفضائية
And what I would like to leave you with is the following question:
وأرغب في ترككم مع هذه الأسئلة:
If you had access to imagery of the whole planet every single day,
إن كان بإمكانكم الوصول لصور الأرض كل يوم
what would you do with that data?
ما الذي ستفعلونه بهذه البيانات؟
What problems would you solve?
ما هي المشاكل التي ستحلون بها؟
What exploration would you do?
ما هي الاستكشافات التي ستقومون بها؟
Well, I invite you to come and explore with us.
وفي الختام، أنا أدعوكم للاستكشاف معنا
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)